Shibuya, August 1997
I woke up this morning believing we'd be stealthily
filming Love & Pop in the corner of Shibuya.
Yet, for some reason, we ended up out in the open.
It's like, have they matured or not?
We would be filming the climax scene between
Asano Tadanobu's Captain EO and Hiromi.
There are a lot of people that would get excited,
but I think he would want to protect the weak.
Yeah, he's that kind of guy.
Understood.
Location shooting was proceeding as planned.
At that time Company Matsuo fled our location and went somewhere.
Matsuo got fed up with
filming and headed to Shinjuku.
[AV Director Hirano Katsuyuki]
We're off.
See you!
I'll do my best.
What's your name?
I'm Matanashi Tomoko.
Dressed as they are, these two are going
to have sex while traveling to Hokkaido.
Matsuo, a man of leisure, embarking with
just himself as director, and his actress.
Yes, Matsuo's main profession is an AV director.
Not only that, but a point of view director.
Gotanda, July 1997
The audition for Love & Pop took place on this day.
Filming for the documentary also started on this day.
Despite there only being 3 weeks until
the start of filming, the staff was in a tizzy.
I'm still not entirely sure why Anno
chose Love & Pop of all things to adapt.
Technically speaking, he'd been saying
he wanted it to be like a fake documentary.
And he thought that Love & Pop would
be good for a documentary format.
Asking for everything to be filmed with a
camcorder is like groping around in the dark.
This is very Anno.
I decided to ask Higuchi, who understood
how Anno ticked, about his thoughts.
Do you remember the
feeling of digital camera film?
Oh, uh yes.
For Evangelion, well, the ending was shot with a 16mm,
but Anno originally bought the VX digital
camera to film a "making of" video.
During production, he just kept running
around by himself filming everything.
Filming things left and right.
Ever since then, his interest in
digital cameras kept growing.
I heard that, but the way we're
filming feels more like a drama.
In the beginning, he has a tendency to be really gung-ho about it.
We don't need any weird shaking.
Wouldn't it be better to station it in a corner?
Anno's the kind of guy to say mid-production that he knew how everything would turn out from the beginning.
Really, now?
Yeah.
Wonder why that is...
Undecided on whether it
was a documentary or a drama,
the auditions were essentially a job to find a Hiromi they envisioned.
Having these girls butter up a bunch of old men with cameras to get a role
was like compensation was dating taking place right in front of us.
I want you to film Anno breaking down.
That was the only request for
this making-of documentary.
Maybe he broke down after working
on Eva? Following his own characters.
Oh, that's why.
Keeping in mind of the original
approach to filming a fake documentary...
with a digital camera for
TV Tokyo's late night spot,
we proceeded with production as normal.
Filming Love & Pop as a
documentary stemmed from this idea.
With that idea as its roots,
the camera took its first shots.
Is it a drama?
Is it a documentary?
Everyone waited for the answer.
We're out of time!
Thinking we might have to abandon everything mid-production,
we were left confused by Anno's thought process.
Love & Pop Special Showing
The lead role went to Miwa Asumi.
What do I do?
I've never been in a drama. This is my first time.
It's just...
extreme levels of nervous.
Love & Pop was gradually turning towards
the normal movie production system.
Before we started filming I decided to ask Anno about his thoughts on this.
What I want to see?
I guess I want to figure that out as I film.
It's pretty vague. I don't have
a clear idea of what I want yet.
Proposal wise...
I'm just not sure.
It's like, uh...
Like an ever-flowing rush of water.
This time it's the amount of water between
me and the 4 girls. It's never ending.
I have to put a lot of
effort into bridging that gap,
but I wonder what would happen if I
filmed with the gap still in place?
It's fun to bounce the ideas around.
And so, filming of Love & Pop started.
It was the beginning of a very
long month and a half of filming.
The filming proceeded according to the
script as a drama and not a documentary.
We retook the same shot
over and over and over again.
Sorry, sorry. We're moving locations.
Matsuo was surprised with the amount of
cuts since he usually works with sex scenes.
After 15 takes we're finally done.
Please, no more takes.
Let's just hurry up and finish.
This film is taking so long...
Why is it that Matsuo, the AV director, is on set now, anyways?
Before production started, producer Nanri said:
"Instead of focusing on a making of
video, focus on a documentary of Anno."
Matsuo misunderstood thinking,
"I must see this task to the end!"
The beginning of
that misunderstanding.
Matsuo's partner in crime, AV director Baksheesh Yamashita, said:
"Megu is a cutie~"
The only part Matsuo
enjoyed was getting food.
Filming was proceeding.
Eventually, the documentary
started taking shape.
Despite being one to usually speak his
mind, Anno is quietly on his best behavior.
Will he ever break?
The only interesting part was that Anno never
eats meat or fish, so meals usually look like this.
With this being the most interesting thing,
the documentary filming fell stagnant.
By the way, my name is Torihada Minoru.
A fruit-loving Japanese Communist Party member.
While working from 8am to the next day's 8am
in the bread factory, I helped to film this movie.
But everything I filmed was cut.
Filming moved to a love hotel.
Apparently, the plan is to film through the night.
"I paid for that girl" happens over there.
It's a love hotel, yet everyone decided to
continue production instead of watch porn.
Both the staff and actors silently focused on their job.
No one had any interest in the vending
machine outside selling vibrators.
Everyone was concentrating all their
efforts towards working on the project.
They even spent the night
there so not to waste time.
Ok, scene 185, cut J, track 1, camera 4.
Camera 3.
Are you hungry?
No.
A whole night working with a
high schooler at a love hotel.
I wonder how many guys would bust from that?
Unfortunately, this is the reality of it.
Let's try one more time.
Alright, one more time.
They're pretty used to their lines but...
They decided to change up their attitude toward
the girls, and focus on filming in the morning.
We'll finish what needs to get
done. It's just a minor set back.
If they come, then it's fine, but we can't ask them.
Captain EO, fundamentally doesn't understand people.
Ok.
From the start, he never saw a
necessity to get along with others.
Like, it's fine this way.
Ok.
But he has another side to him.
He begins to blame himself.
The only one who can talk
him through it is himself.
If he thinks he can't do it,
then it becomes a mental block.
He has an image in his head and she doesn't fit that image.
I think his mother is to blame.
It just feels like that.
If your mother does something when you're that
sad and crying, then you start to lose yourself.
He put revenge against women second.
He takes a different approach
when dealing with society.
By taking revenge on other women, he is getting
what he really wants: revenge on his mother.
That's how his "relationships" progress.
It's awful.
It's not really normal to
talk with the director on set.
But even then, he's the one
doing most of the talking.
I don't have to say a lot.
Before the filming started, there was free time
and I really think I should have talked some more.
Alright, wait.
Move forward.
Scene 189, cut I, track 1,
Ok, scene 189, cut J, track 1.
Scene 189, cut J, track 2.
Even the staff was unable to mask the fatigue that the hard filming schedule hurdle was setting.
People were dropping
like flies one after the other.
Regardless, filming continued in the morning.
By the way, the request of "I want you to
film Anno breaking down" was by this man.
Since things weren't very thrilling on
set, the two documentary guys took off.
Filming. Ready, start.
What are you going to ask god for?
- And cut.
- Alright cut.
We are just following customers' orders
and thus are innocent under the law.
Um, do you think you can go
back in front of Mitsukoshi?
Yamashita decided to hear some real stories
from his acquaintance from a sex chat line.
The first time I did it was my first year of high school.
With my friends.
We waited in Ikebukuro for a guy to
ask us, and one did really quickly.
So we went to karaoke together first.
When my friend masturbated, she earned 30,000 yen.
I didn't do much, so I only got 20,000 yen.
My friends and boyfriend know so I just
tell them when I'm heading off to work.
When I first did it, I thought, "Oh my god this is bad."
But I've gotten used to it.
I didn't know what I'd do if my
boyfriend or parents found out.
My friend has this crazy amazing guy.
He paid 70,000 yen and then ran away
while she was taking a shower in the love hotel.
I've never had a bad experience
and I've never heard of one.
So do you have sex?
Yeah.
What's going on in your head during that time.
I just kind of think.
About what?
Money.
It's a rather boring story, but at least
there was something juicy to her story.
Matsuo was meeting with a woman in Takadanobaba.
What?
Self-defense?
Self-defense.
How old are you?
I'm 28.
28? You don't look it.
Oh, was...I not supposed to say?
It's ok.
Sorry.
No problem here.
I'm 22.
They decided to take the
interview to the bathroom.
We talk...
This is how his usual workday goes, so of course
he would complain about filming normal movies.
Do you know any anime?
I don't watch too much anime anymore,
but I really liked it when I was little.
Even when I got older I liked stuff like
Slam Dunk. I watched it every week.
Have you seen Evangelion?
Eva... No I haven't.
Do you know who made it?
No idea...
As far as anime directors go, I only know,
like, Miyazaki Hayao and Oshii Mamoru.
I really like Oshii Mamoru.
Your name?
Honda Karen.
Back on set, filming was finally picking up.
Midway, I want you to ask who Mizuaki is.
Underwear.
Undress down to underwear.
Under her underwear she'll have a singlet.
She's not wearing underwear.
Not wearing them?
Nanri had taken command of production
and things were progressing smoothly.
We won't film it.
We'll only show her underwear around her
ankle. Then there'll be the skirt and underwear...
Yeah that's fine.
- It's fine?
- Yeah, yeah.
It was time for the punishment scene in the bathroom.
Miwa is a bit nervous.
Did you practice how you were
going to choreograph this?
I did with Nanri.
I had it explained to me by Nanri and my manager and was able to ask questions.
Basically, I have to trust Nanri.
Just waiting now.
And the director?
He said as long as I trust Nanri it's all good.
He said it's all good, so I guess I'll believe him.
For this next scene...
When you two are facing each other like this.
Anno has once again taken
interest in Asano's acting.
Lift up by her head and bring her towards you.
Bring her close and finish?
Kind of like, "You, come here."
Bring her over here.
Will you be fine for this scene?
You can go till the end?
All the way until the end.
If she doesn't go down, force the helmet down.
Understood.
She has that padding on the back of her.
Let's get out of here.
- Ok, ok.
- Leaving.
Here we go!
Ready
Start!
With such a short schedule, it's not guaranteed that everyone will end up friends.
Miscommunications can happen,
which is a theme I hit on a lot.
Acting tough or going with the flow is seen as the right thing to do.
You either have the ability to do it or don't.
What kind of person is Anno?
He's a very interesting and odd person.
In the beginning he didn't
give that much support.
He's still like that. I don't know what he's thinking.
Are you ok?
Do you want to leave?
Go to the bathroom, practice,
and then we'll wing the rest.
If that doesn't work...
You'll look naked, but the important parts will be covered up.
Got it?
Awesome, next.
Thank you!
Thank you.
2 days, roughly 36 hours of shooting, wrap up.
They overcame one hurdle,
but a long road still lay ahead.
While the hard schedule slowly wore them
down, their reassurance in the project went up.
It wasn't pressure of a short schedule, it was
being able to see the light at the end of the tunnel.
That's the kind of expression they showed.
One month later, all filming completed
and post production was about to begin.
What will you do about the ring?
I don't want to give it up, but haven't the nerve.
Miwa was able to muster up her
spunk to perform her role as intended.
Anno's Love & Pop was completed.
The documentary was unable
to capture its intended footage.
We had to face these facts of all the wasted time
and went on with our presentation.
Anno Hideaki (New Director)
Love & Pop Documentary
Final Part
Bad Summer
Dammit!