Disclaimer: What you are about to see is
special "Hideaki Anno" making-of documentary.
Bear in mind while watching and please enjoy.
November 12th, 1997. Imagica
A month before the official premiere,
we're at the press presentation.
Love & Pop Documentary
Part 0
[Last Scene]
A roar of applause filled the room as the
last scene in the Shibuya River played.
It's pretty difficult to film with your average camcorder.
I'm so glad that I was able to
participate in the creation of this movie.
Anno's Group [Love & Pop] Staff Room
July, 1997 Filming Room
Two weeks before the showing,
there was a meeting about the script.
Finally we go to Miyako Island, as a
way to break away from the ordinary.
It's a sort of liberating paradise for the girls.
At least from an old man's perspective.
From a young person's perspective,
they might wonder why.
But if they go, they'll understand how
good the sand and the sun feels.
We're not delving into that, though.
That's what I want to believe, but people watching...
The last scene in the
southern island is proving difficult.
I'm worried people will watch and think,
"Why the heck are these schoolgirl trying to
liberate themselves." Stop messing around!
They won't see what is being conveyed.
I, obviously, don't have real
experience being a high school girl.
This is the reality of our problem.
Regardless...we have to hurry up and overcome that.
I think as long as we don't get
dragged down by it we should be fine.
And so filming began.
In an instant, it was almost over.
September, 1997. Okinawa Miyako Island
After fighting through filming in Tokyo,
We switched out our heavy equipment and
moved to the islands for a final 3 day, 2 night trip.
This was all to film the troubling final scene.
Before the script was finished, Anno imagined it
would end with the girls in the southern island.
Oh, poor uniform.
But...
Ah, gross!
Ah, so gross!
Not only was the last scene shot here,
but the opening montage, as well.
Filming was proceeding as planned.
Before filming the last scene,
the staff gathered together.
The film would surely turn out beautiful.
"I can sense the blessing of the
film" was written in the script.
Anno was in high spirits.
Oh, scary, scary.
The girls were having no
problem enjoying their time.
They were very pretty.
Even though Love & Pop is a feature film, everything
up to this point was all filmed on a generic camcorder.
- Ready?
- Let go.
We're starting!
- Ok!
- Alright.
Ready...
Go!
The entirety of this last
scene was a tracking shot.
Cut, cut, cut.
Cut!
Come back!
Get back here!
Go!
Chisa, what are you doing?!
Filming was proceeding as planned.
The only thing not on schedule was
me, Sato, the assistant camera man.
Got it.
You haven't put this in yet?
I'm sorry.
What?
I had just graduated from school, and
didn't have much on-set experience.
Being on set is a race against time.
Sato, are you ready?
Sato! Now is not the time to change the film roll!
Leave it!
I wasn't familiar with changing out film,
so it took longer than it should have.
The cameraman, Shibanushi, was glaring.
Sato! Sato! Now...Now is not
the time to change the film roll!
Ding ding
In the end, the film we got fell into the sand.
Anno said, "No problem. We'll just film tomorrow."
The sunset was very bright.
To wrap up the days filming,
we had a BBQ party that night.
Unable to show left side of screen.
Director Anno was in a very good mood.
He cast off his cool demeanor just like that.
Dawn of the 2nd day, 4 a.m.
We started with a scene alongside the sunrise.
It was a very energizing shot.
Underwater filming was also going well.
Everything was proceeding as planned.
But, I messed up again.
Sato!
Sato! Sato! Now...Now is not
the time to change the film roll!
I dropped the film into the ocean.
Because of that, the actress playing Hiromi got
depressed and we couldn't continue filming.
Everything was my fault.
This had been our last day to film the sunset.
I thought I would go and apologize to the girls.
However, they were dead tired.
How many do you want?
Hiromi's actress was especially worn out.
Did you hear what we're doing after dinner?
What?
Karaoke.
I knew that.
There's also an arcade.
I knew that!
An arcade?
All we can do is enjoy ourselves now, right?
If you're gonna have fun you gotta go to the arcade.
Yeah let's just have fun.
You can come and not sing if you want.
...karaoke...
After dinner, Anno and Nanri were having a conversation.
There's a feeling that they don't want to be saved.
But if we show it like they're
some kind of 70s pop idols,
I feel like some guys will
understand, so it'll work out.
If we have to change the ending, then we have
to change the ending. That's all there is to it.
Honestly, I think we should go home.
This song, "Happy" is a happy song for everyone all over the world!
All over the world.
No matter where you are, there's love!
Kind of like, why are you giving it to me?
But you know, I think when you
saw Hiromi having fun in the ocean,
when you saw that live, you thought,
"Wait, I don't actually want this."
Ok, but listen, that's what acting is.
Not lowering your standards.
I feel like you won't be able to hold out.
That's fine.
It's more natural to not be able to hold out.
Like, "Ahhh, I can't do this anymore."
Breaking because of that is fine.
If the problem stems from you,
then you have to break down eventually.
But it's something that was broken from the
outside, so I'm not sure how to make it work.
You think, "I'll break this." Then it escapes and suddenly, "Oh!"
It's broken by someone else.
You have to take the broken bits
and quickly fix what you can.
Do this, this breaks.
How are the girls doing?
Did they fall asleep?
Let them sleep if they want.
Who cares?
I mean...
Should we... No, we don't need to bother them.
Oh yeah, are we going to invite them to karaoke?
Nope.
Is it broken?
They're panicking.
Probably just a cold.
No, no, no. I've been told I'm a gloomy person.
By the way, even though he's always on my
case, Shibanushi is actually a good person.
They told me to act happier so they gave me a sweater—a red sweater,
and told me to get it together.
I bet it's cause you were poor.
And so it was decided we would re-film the last scene the next day.
There was also the idea of ending with
the girls in swimsuits in the Shibuya river.
The river...
What?
We aren't getting the expressions we want
at the beach, so our plan is falling through.
What about the girls going down Shibuya
river in swimsuits. That's pretty cool.
It's cool, I'm not doubting that. If that's how
the script was from the beginning it would be fine.
It would be difficult for
people to grasp what's going on.
We can send them off, but the problem starts there.
Anno caught a brief glimpse of Kirari's underwear.
We only have one shot at this.
We're going in the water like this?
Of course!
It was our last day and the everyone
on set was wracked with nerves.
No laughing.
The girls were also taking this seriously.
If we failed this time, we might as well die.
My nerves were also at their peak.
Ready...start.
I don't remember what happened after this.
Before I knew it, I was running
away with the film we had just shot.
Why did I take the film and run?
I also have no idea.
All I knew was the feeling of the tape
swaying and how beautifully blue the sky was.
That is how I ruined all of the
film taken in the southern islands.
We were done with location shooting.
The clouds were crying.
All of this was extra film so
I decided to put it to good use.
I put them together and handed
them over as a documentary.
Love & Pop
Part 0
Last Scene
In collaboration with all the Love & Pop staff.
A roar of applause filled the room as the
last scene in the Shibuya River played.
I'm going to try my absolute best
to become a great filmmaker.
The end.